now that we have discussed the context
switch let's
go through some basic concepts about processes
so now I'm going to say stuff that
it's detailing a bit better
what I just show you about the context switch
so what the computer executes is called process
we don't use the term program because
the program is
a passive entity it is what is stored on disk while
the process
is the program
once you start executing it
when you execute it you load it into
memory
you can start of course programs and processes
in different
ways the important thing here is that you
can have a program
that is composed of several processes
and some processes can also be the execution
environment
for other processes
and this is the example of the Java virtual machine
when you want to run a process you need
to maintain
information that belongs to the process itself
so you need a portion of memory in which you
place the process
but the operating system
needs also to maintain
information
about the process I mentioned before that
for instance
you need to know whether a process is running
or it's idle
this is not information that belongs
to the process
it's information the operating system maintains
about the
process if we focus on the information that
belongs to the
process then we have different parts
there is the program code or the text section
this is basically where you keep the instructions
that you
have to run to execute your process
there is the data section that contains global
variables and
then there is the heap and the stack
the heap contains memory that is dynamically
allocated while
you execute the process while the stack contains
temporary
data function parameters return
addresses local
variables and so now this scheme here shows
you the different
states in which your process can be
when you tell the operating system to run
a certain program
by creating a process the operating system
sets the process
state initially to new so the process is being
created
once everything is ready the process goes
into the ready
state okay ready means that it's not executing
but it
can start to execute if it's given a CPU
core
remember that
only one process can be running at each processor
CPU core at
any instant
from ready you can go to running
if the process is actually given access to
the CPU core
it stays into the running state until it generates
maybe
a request for which it needs input or output
so it says i want to read something from the
disk
for instance
in that case the process cannot continue until
it gets what
it needs from the disk
but when there is I/O it doesn't
go back to ready
because it's not really ready to start again
until the disk
answers or the I/O is completed
because of this it goes into a waiting state
and once what the process is waiting for is
received it
goes back to ready because that is the point
at which it's
actually ready to run again
of course you can also go directly from running
to ready if the
clock for example generates and interrupt
the process gets stopped because something
else needs to
run but the process is not asking for some
kind of I/O
so it can just go back to the ready
state
and finally once you are running you might
also decide
to exit and be terminated once you execute
your last instruction
this is the context switch I presented before
so when the CPU switches to another process
we said that
the system must save information about what
it was doing
and what it will be doing next
because of this it stores the information
about the process
not the information on the process itself
that stays in memory
and this information is what is contained
in the process
control block or PCB
as I said context switches are an overhead
so you want to minimize the time it takes
to do the context
switch and you also want to minimize how many
context switches
you do if possible
and you need support from the hardware
you need for example interrupt from the clock
that periodically
allow the operating system to wake up and
check what
is happening
this is the information we have in the process
control block
you can read the slide by yourself but just
to point out
some interesting stuff one important thing
is the program
counter which is basically the location of
the next instruction
to execute or better
said the address in the main memory that belongs
to the text
section of a certain process in which the
next instruction
to be run is stored
you can have registers
from the
CPU you can have accounting information about
CPU used or
time elapsed and so on information about input
output whether
the process is waiting for something or not
and so on just have a look at this list